for my first job I was technically hired
as a front-end developer but things
weren't that clear-cut on my team and
for my first task I found myself having
to dive into Python code the problem was
I had never formally learned Python and
I found myself having to use it a lot to
do my job no problem I thought learning
on the job is the best way to learn and
I do firmly believe that that being said
I had to struggle to figure out basic
things a few of which would have made my
life so much easier in those early days
of using Python so here's five tips and
tricks you can start using right away to
improve your Python experience the first
trick is the interactive shell let's say
I have a Python file with a function
that adds two numbers now conventionally
I might call this function at the bottom
of my file and then run the file with
the Python keyword but there's another
way I can run this function and that is
with the interactive shell so instead of
Python main dot py I add the - I flag
for interactive now I can call this
function in a shell like this this can
be really useful for developing things
like thoughts if you've seen my tinder
bot video we control our web scraper
through this interface so this will load
your Python file but then instead of
closing after running the code it will
give you access to all the functions and
variables inside so again this is a
great way to do development testing and
it can make you feel like a god when you
have the interactive shell at your
disposal issuing commands at will tip
number two is PDB the Python debugger
while Python - I will run your entire
file then give you an interface into
that environment PDB can stop your file
before it's finished executing so you
can debug I'll give you an example if
I'm adding one and two and then I'm
adding one and some character that
shouldn't be there I will get an error
when I try to run this file
but let's say this file is huge and I
don't know where the error is occurring
in that case I can import PDB the Python
debugger that's built in a Python and
then call the set trace method to pause
the execution of my code now I'll get
this weird kind of interface that says
PDB where I can do different things like
print the current values of variables
and functions or I can go to the next
line with n for next so again this can
help me identify where my code is
breaking and I can even follow the
debugger through complex multiple levels
of function calls the great part is you
can import PDB in lines so you don't
even have to do it at the top of the
file and then you can just delete this
when you're done number 3 the virtual
environment a big part of the reason
Python is so dominant is because of how
many good libraries it has in fact
python has so many good math statistics
data analysis libraries that it will
probably be around for quite a long time
that being said the dependency
management can be a bit annoying in
other words how do you confine the
libraries you need to a specific project
making it shareable and portable one of
the ways we accomplish this is through
virtual environments the most used one
is called virtual end and you can
install it with pip install virtual end
once you do that you can create a new
environment with virtual end followed by
the name of the folder your environments
in and then you can install the
dependencies you need for the project so
you do this by activating the virtual
environment by sourcing the end bin
activate now you'll see this little
prefix in my terminal prompt meaning it
is active now I can install any
dependencies in isolation so let's say I
wanted to develop a a bot I can pip
install selenium the pendency that I
might need and it will just be in this
VN folder anyway I don't want to get too
deep into dependencies but just know
that generally working in a virtual
environment is the best practice when
you're using Python number for list and
dict
comprehension let's say you have some
data a list of fruits with
prices and names represented as a dict
it's a pretty common use case to want to
pull out a single property from an
object but to do that in conventional
syntax we have to do something like this
so it does work but it also takes four
lines and a lot of typing just to get
this done so there is actually a way to
do this with one line and that's with
list comprehension this is kind of weird
syntax that's only occurs in Python but
when you get used to it and if you're
not scared of it kind of like I was then
it can really come in handy so within
these brackets I'll type a loop like
syntax essentially it's giving me each
item in the list in a second variable
over here and with this variable I can
modify the output so this is what will
go into our new list I print this out
we'll get the same result as before now
that's not all we can do with list
comprehension we can also append things
like conditional statements to the end
for example if our fruit starts with an
A then it will filter that list down as
well okay let's talk about dict
comprehension which is kind of similar
to this this time let's create a dict
that has a fruit name as the key and the
price is the value so again normally we
would have to loop through each one of
these manually add them to a dict but in
this case we can just do that in one
line so I would do this with this syntax
and printing that out I can see it
worked
so again this part looks the same it's
just a normal loop but then we set our
key and our value over here with that
second variable that's created from
looking at each item tip number five is
to use the lambda I think the name
sounded mathy but a lambda is just
exactly the same thing as a function
with a different syntax let me show you
what I mean so we have a function for ad
and I'm gonna make another function add
to that has a lambda so it turns out and
if I open this with a interactive shell
these two are exactly the same so what
it is is just a different syntax now
where does this come in handy and why
would you not always use lambda well
this one is quite a bit easier to read
and reason about what you're doing also
if you have multi-line complex functions
you definitely want to put them in a def
now lambdas very good for example if you
wanted to define a function in your
interactive shell that's one case that I
often use them and another probably more
common example is in list methods that
need a callback function for example
sorting mapping and filtering so let's
just use the filter function as an
example which takes as an argument a
function that will be applied to all the
items as well as lists so if I print
that out in list format I'm gonna have
any list of all the numbers greater than
one now this is kind of a lot of code
again for what we're trying to do so one
way to do this would be to use less
comprehension in fact for this example
that would probably be a better way or
well you could again
this the one line using a lambda so I'm
gonna delete that function write a
lambda directly in here as an argument
and then use a pretty clean syntax just
like that now just to make it one line
I'm gonna move it directly in here as
well and we'll get the same result so
again there are a lot of cases where
you'll want to use a function as an
argument and lambdas are great in that
case too
I hope you guys found that useful like
the video if you learned something new
subscribe for more quick tips and tricks
and tutorials and this is code rip I
will catch you guys soon