Welcome to the genomic medicine GEM
produced by the division of genomic
medicine at UC Davis. This module will
focus on what genomic medicine is, how it
came to be and a few of the ways that
genomic medicine is impacting the world
we live in. The NHGRI defines genomic
medicine as "An emerging medical
discipline that involves using genomic
information about an individual as part
of their clinical care and the health
outcomes and policy implications of
that clinical use".  Let's take a step back
for a moment and reflect on how the
field of genomic medicine came to be,
you've probably heard of the Human
Genome Project formerly launched in 1990,
the human genome projects goal was to
determine the sequence of base pairs
that comprise human DNA and to map all
the genes of the human genome. The
project was determined complete in 2003,
two years ahead of schedule and it cost
around three billion dollars. At the time
the project was launched, the belief was
that having the sequence of all 3.3
billion nucleotides in the human genome
would allow us to understand diseases
such as cancer, diabetes, viruses and
improve in fields such as forensics,
anthropology and agriculture. While it's
true that the completion of the human
genome project was a huge step in the
right direction for all these fields,
there's still considerable work to be
done to understand and interpret the
genome; for example, one current task at
hand is to identify the genetic variants
that increase the risk for human
diseases, genomic medicine then strives
to utilize genomic information to help
make clinical recommendations to improve
health outcomes. Already genomic medicine
is making a tremendous impact in the
fields of oncology, pharmacology,
preconception and prenatal, pediatrics
rare and undiagnosed diseases, infectious
diseases and many more. In the past few
years there has been a growing push for
personalized or precision medicine to
reach the clinic, where specific
individuals unique genome, epigenome,
environmental exposure, family history
and other data can be assessed to tailor
a clinical recommendation to that
patient. Some specific examples of
applications of precision medicine
include pharmacogenomics which uses
genomic information to ensure that
patients are getting the right dose
of the right drug, cancer and
immunotherapy treatments which target
specific molecular markers or the
patient's immune system to enhance its
cancer fighting capabilities and
personalized lifestyle plans which
utilize genomic information to make
fitness and dietary recommendations
specific to an individual. Other advances
actively being studied and tested
include stem-cell therapy and
regenerative medicine, gene editing
techniques like CRISPR/CAS9 which
allows permanent modification of genes
within organisms, base editing or
chemical surgery which like CRISPR has
the potential to alter bases in the
genome of an organism, all of these
methodologies just mentioned are still
emerging and will continue to improve
over time. The field of genomic medicine
is still emerging and very quickly
advancing many academic and research
institutions such as UC Davis now have
their own genomic medicine groups. Some
institutions like UC Davis also have or
are developing divisions of precision
medicine or precision Diagnostics,
more of these are likely to appear in
the near future. The division of genomic
medicine at UC Davis aims to combine
clinical information with genomic
information to make recommendations and
improve health outcomes. The team of
clinical providers consists of medical
geneticists, genetic counselors,
pediatricians, social workers and
dieticians. If you would like to learn
more about genomic medicine or the
division of genomic medicine at UC Davis,
please feel free to get in touch. You can
visit our clinic at the MIND Institute
on the medical campus in Sacramento,
visit our website or call us with
questions or to speak with a genetic
counselor.